Let me start this week's lecture, or the lecture
videos for this week, with some remarks here
on the whiteboard, again, both refreshing
some aspects of expression style that were
discussed last week, but also already discussing
a few aspects or observations I made from
the first exercise submissions
(of a previous year).
So, usually, I try to do this, to have a look
at the exercise submissions before the lecture
and then comment on things that I observed
and seem important or interesting for the
lecture.
I don't know whether this will often be possible
this year because [... outdated comments ...]
So, in this case, one day before the lecture,
but in other cases, maybe I will even record
videos two days or earlier before the lecture.
And then I don't want, of course,
to spoil too much from the exercise.
Okay, anyway, so a few small things I can
discuss now because at least I had a look
at the first submissions, even though
not all of them are yet in the system.
So let me discuss a few small things first.
One thing is syntax.
That is something that I commented on
already in last week's lecture and examples.
And the dominant thing, also what Autotool
was pointing out in the first submissions,
things like student submissions
consisting of, or containing code
like this.
So, a call of the 'translated' function with
two arguments for the x and y direction, and
then some rectangle or whatever.
And then if you look carefully, then Autotool
in a submission like this would have told you
that these brackets are unnecessary, and would
even suggest that you should write just five
and three there.
We were not yet punishing this.
So, these suggestions that Autotool gives
you are really just suggestions yet.
But I still encourage you to read that
feedback and also act on it, because sooner
or later, we will enforce
more of these suggestions.
So, they will actually become mandatory things
and then you have to change your code, because
otherwise it will not be accepted.
And you don't want this, in
the interest of correctness.
And so, it's a good habit to, early on, really
read the feedback that Autotool is giving
you.
So that you can both improve your code and
actually later not be frustrated because Autotool
doesn't even accept your submissions because
they violate certain style and other
guidelines that we enforce.
Okay.
And I also know, and I've seen that in some
cases in the first week, the Autotool feedback
contained some junk or some… in particular,
the first few submissions of students that
have submitted, had some comments in their
Autotool feedback that didn't really make
sense; something about some part of the code
only appearing in their submission, that was
actually a small bug in Autotool, that it printed
something that it wasn't supposed to print
in these places.
So, this has been fixed
and shouldn't occur again.
So, the general remark is you should
read the feedback and act on it.
And a few students will actually, in the first
week, have gotten some feedback that they couldn't
really have acted on, because
that didn't make much sense.
But that should be an exception
and shouldn't occur again, we hope.
Okay.
So, this was a general syntax remark,
which applied to quite a few submissions.
And then I actually want to make a more semantic
and more interesting remark discussing one
particular submission, not because it was bad
or anything; actually, it's an interesting
submission.
And I won't reproduce it completely, but I
want to show some parts of it and use that
for a discussion of expression style,
which is somehow fits quite nicely.
Okay, so there was this task of drawing this
tree and without giving a full solution here,
because that's what the exercises are for.
And I want to show part of, or a sketch of one
solution that I saw in one of the first submissions
looked something like this; I will
omit all the type annotations.
So, there was something like this, the scene
value that was composed out of a few components,
and among them, that was the leaves, right,
because this tree was supposed to have some
leaves.
So, there was some definition, then the
leaves, how were the leaves defined?
Well, there was a separate definition.
And again, that consisted of some subexpressions,
and one of them was something like a rotated
circle.
So, the name of some other expressions, some
other picture that occurred somewhere in
the middle of a larger expression, then this
rotated circle was defined as something like:
We call this function for moving a picture
with some arguments, something like
this.
And what was it?
What was moved?
Well, some call of the 'rotated' function with
some arguments, something like pi over four.
And of what?
Well, of some green form that was supposed
to be part of the leaves, apparently.
And how was that green form defined?
Well, again, in a separate definition.
And that was a “colored” call, of course,
because it's supposed to be a green form.
And what is “colored”?
Well, in this case, it was a solid
circle with some radius, 2 or so.
Okay.
So, and then there was, of course,
a completion of this whole thing.
So, that was a working
program. Everything's fine.
Okay, some observations on this.
Well, one thing I would observe, and that
applies really to a lot of the submissions,
is the balance between top-level
definitions and local definitions, right?
There was a long file, where
many more forms were defined
in the same way.
And all of them got a top-level name and
then appeared in this long list of things.
That's okay.
But actually, I would argue that probably
most of these definitions could also be just
used as a local definition.
So, I would encourage you, if you encounter a
situation like this in the exercise, where you write
many definitions, that maybe you think
about not having this green form on the top
level, but for example, adding
it here as a local definition.
Yes, we have seen this in last week's examples,
that you can also write a definition
here. It's somehow more logically grouped.
Okay, that's a general remark that applies
to a lot of the submissions I have seen.
Again, it doesn't mean that
what you see here is wrong.
It's just a general remark that you
could make more use of local definitions.
But actually, there's some other thing
that surprised me here, when I saw this.
And basically, it's mainly
this name: rotatedCircle.
I was wondering why would I rotate a circle?
A circle is a round thing that doesn't really
have orientations.
Why would I rotate a circle?
And indeed, if you look at the closest example,
you will probably realize, and you could even
try it out if you have the solution in front
of you, that you probably don't need this
rotated call.
Yes, you could think about it and say, well,
I don't need to rotate the circle, because
anyway, it doesn't change
its form by just rotation.
This is one way to look at it.
But then, of course, there's also the question
of whether you could argue this in general?
Or could you prove this?
Or is this something that you could do as
part of refactoring once you see such code.
For example, it's not my code,
it's someone else's code.
So, I'm maybe not sure whether just going by
this name, maybe that's not enough indication
that I should really change it, maybe
this name is simply not appropriate.
So, what could I do in order to improve this
program or change this program to convince
myself whether or not I really
need this rotation of a circle?
Well, let's look at it.
And let's look at it in this
expression style, and approach.
So, let's actually build an expression and
think about whether I can manipulate this
expression just as in mathematics
I manipulate formulas.
If I see something like x + y × (p + c), or
whatever and it looks too complicated, then I also
start applying algebraic laws to change this
formula, simplifying maybe into something where
I see a better solution, or
that's a simpler solution.
Okay, so let's try to apply the same habit
here and try to simplify this program just
as you would simplify an arithmetic expression.
Okay, and well, in order to do this, maybe
I should first really make one expression
out of this.
And I can do this because I can simply inline
these definitions, as you know, and as we
discussed last week, these definitions here
are not somehow assignment statements, they
are just giving names to subexpressions.
Yes, so of course, I can also inline or
put those parts of expressions that I want
to think about into one closed line.
So, exactly since this rotated
circle was what I was thinking
about, and thinking about whether
I could somehow change it.
Let me actually take this expression and write
it down in full without this indirection by
naming the subexpression.
What do I get then?
I get this complex or a bit
more complex expression.
So, copying what I have above.
Let me actually write this as a variable name,
like in Haskell instead of this mathematical
pi.
And then instead of the green form here, I can
really simply put in a definition of a green
form.
That's exactly what it means
to have named a subexpression.
So, what I can then think about
is “colored”.
And then I need an appropriate
number of brackets.
Okay, so this is the
expression I'm thinking about.
And it's the same as this, right?
I've simply written it all in one
long line, one long expression.
Okay, so what do I see here now, I
really have my rotation and my circle in
the same context where I could think about
where is it needed to really rotate that circle?
And how could I do this?
Or how could I think about this?
What I could think about is that there are some
laws maybe, just as in mathematics, we have
laws, like x + y = y + x.
If I want to apply the same approach here
to a graphical expression, let me actually
think about laws.
Yes, this is my expression I'm interested in.
Let me think about not only
what to do
with this expression, but a general idea
of what's going on, let me think about
a law.
Just like a mathematical law, like commutativity,
or anything like that, but on these operations.
So, one thing I could imagine that is true,
is something like that: "rotated", with some
argument (I don't need to have the pi over
two or something, I can take an arbitrary
angle), and a solid circle, and probably
the same holds for a normal circle.
But since I have a solid circle
above it, let me do this.
And again, the radius of the circle is not
important, whether it's two or three, or whatever.
So, let me take just a variable for this as
well.
Then I could say, well, probably there should
be a law which says, if I rotate a circle,
that's really the same thing.
And let me use the symbol for semantically
equivalent (the equal sign from mathematics,
basically). Well, the rotated circle is
really just that circle of the same radius.
And the angle by which to rotate is irrelevant,
because I don't even need to rotate the circle.
Okay, but that's probably my
intuition why I was thinking:
a rotated circle doesn't really
make much sense.
It's just a circle.
So, this law somehow exactly incorporates
this inspiration or this thinking I had.
Okay.
However, that doesn't really apply here, right,
you don't have something of the form rotated
of an angle of a circle.
That's not what we see here.
And just as in mathematics, you
cannot apply the distributive law.
if you don't have the correct shape. In
our mathematical expression, we need more.
So actually, we don't need just one law.
But maybe more than one, maybe additional
laws.
Let's think about more laws.
If I, for example, want to be able to apply
this, then probably I should somehow get this
“rotated” further inside.
Just as in mathematics, you will sometimes just
have to do some steps in order to ultimately
really be able to apply, for
example, the distributive law.
So, some other useful law would be… and then
we can think about whether it's actually true.
But something that would be useful here, in
order to apply the first law would be if you
had something like: if you rotate something
which is colored, so if we have a variable
for the color c,
and for some picture p, which could be anything
(anything that is a picture), then well, what
would we have?
You could say, well, to rotate a colored picture
is the same as coloring a rotated picture,
that would certainly be useful
in the above expression.
So, let's say or let's make a hypothesis: This
is the same as basically switching these two
calls.
So, we're taking a picture, coloring it and
then rotating it by some angle. Is it the
same as taking the picture, first
rotating it, and then coloring it?
And well, whether this is true or not depends on
the library, of course, on the implementation,
but if the implementation somehow is really
the library that we use, the CodeWorld library
is really implementing meaningful versions of
rotation, coloring, and picture primitives,
then that's probably a law
that you also expect to hold.
And of course, for other ones, we could also
have further laws, like for example, it says
similar things about what it means
to move a colored picture, etc.
So basically, for all or many of the combinations
of our picture primitives, we could think
about laws.
Okay.
Now let's assume that these are valid, (these
laws), then with these two together, we could
actually switch the order of these two calls,
and then eliminate the “rotated” because it
sees a solid circle.
And this means, at least if I put this r here,
that actually we can eliminate it completely.
Okay, so let me actually fix
this and put the radius here.
Okay, and what I've been doing here, or what I
am suggesting here to improve the above program
is really the same as we do in
mathematics when we simplify expressions.
It's simply applied to a different domain,
namely, in this case, the domain of picture
expressions.
So, it's really the same as in mathematics,
arithmetic, to have laws, like a + b is b + a
or a × (b + c) is a × b + a × c.
Okay, that's the same kind of
reasoning or thinking I do here.
Now, is this specific to Haskell
programming or functional programming?
Or could I do this in other languages as
well?
Well, to some extent, you could say,
maybe I can do the same thing in Java.
If in Java, or C, or Python, I do write my
library in a style that I have these primitives,
maybe I could also apply such refactorings to
my programs, which to some extent, is true.
But of course, since Java, or C, or Python
programs are not only or to a large extent,
even expressed in terms of nested function
calls, there is not that much opportunity.
It's not like mathematics, where
everything is an expression.
So certainly, functional programming, or Haskell
programming very much encourages or forces
this style of programming; we are
building expressions like this.
And as soon as we are in a language where that
is not the case, then it might be possible to
do some small modifications, but not in the
same spirit that you will really think about
programs in terms of such transformations.
Okay.
And then you could also say maybe I don't
need these laws, right? I see this expression,
I see what's going on.
So, I simply improve it.
Well, maybe if it was a small
example like that, it's true.
But such common-sense reasoning is
not something that works at scale.
There's a reason that mathematicians do not
just look at equations and say, well, I see
the solution; they really apply laws like
this.
And there's a reason for doing it that way,
because you can prove that something is true.
And you can handle larger examples, then,
or larger problems, than if you would simply
work by common sense and say
I see what the solution is.
And the same applies to programs.
In a small program, maybe it's not
necessary to really work with these laws.
But as soon as you work in the context of a
larger program, it's really helpful to know
why you do some, for example, simplification
steps, and then having laws like this is really
the way to go.
They also actually serve other purposes.
They could be used as documentation
for the API, for the library.
They could, for example, be used for
testing the library / the implementation.
So, once we have our library, and we know
what the functions are, we could think about
useful laws, that should be true.
And then we could make tests of the library to
see whether these laws are really satisfied.
And if they don't, then probably there's a
problem not in our thinking about the property
or operation, but in the
implementation of the library.
Okay.
So, I want to make another excursion,
since I just mentioned Java.
So, could you imagine that the same kind of
approach would work in Java or other languages
that you know?
Let's think about it: could we do
something like this in Java as well?
Well, to some extent, probably, yes.
So, let's think about this in
object-oriented style, for example.
So certainly, you could imagine that if you
introduce methods on a picture class, for
coloring, for rotation, for moving, etc.
you could probably write things like:
if I have a picture, and I color it
(let's say we have a method for this
and it takes a picture argument because
it operates on an object of the class Picture),
and then afterwards, I rotate this by some
angle, then you could probably expect and
establish for some library, that this is the same
as first rotating the picture and then coloring
it.
Yes, so, this is in this spirit.
Definitely very similar to what I gave above
as the second law. And for the other laws, you
could probably write down in many cases, write
down something also in this object-oriented
notation.
Okay, well, that's good luck here in some
sense, because the syntax works nicely in
this way for methods that operate
on exactly one picture, right?
Coloring takes one picture,
rotation works on one picture, etc.
So, for example, already, if you want to do
something for the combination of pictures,
it becomes more complicated.
Yes, so this really doesn't work so nicely for,
for example, binary methods.
So, methods that take two picture arguments.
So, exactly like the combination function,
whereas in a functional expression style setting,
it doesn't really matter how many arguments functions
take. As long as everything is an expression…
If you have a function that
takes three arguments, then
you can still write down
laws about it.
So, there's no problem with this.
And also, actually, just by the way,
object-orientation works, usually, but there are
of course problems
with stuff like the following.
So, let's say we have a picture, and we
want to have a colored version of it.
But we also want to draw the same basic picture
in a different place, but without a new color.
Say we have a triangle, and we want
to move it somewhere, but we also want
to color it red, but these
as two independent things.
We want to have a colored triangle somewhere
and an uncolored triangle somewhere else.
And then that's not really what this expression
would give us right because in this interpretation,
where a method like this operates on the object,
then this would mean if evaluated from left
to right, then this first call will take
our triangle and color it red, for example.
And then the second call would move
the, now red, triangle somewhere
else, right?
Because this will have had an
effect on the p, of writing
some instance variables or setting
the color or something like that.
Okay, well, this is not the same as in mathematics,
where something like this cannot happen.
Just because we have some call of “colored” on p in
some part of the expression, it doesn't mean that
other occurrences of the same expression
will also magically change their color.
That's because of side effects,
imperative programming, etc.
Okay, and well, finally, coming back
to another aspect from last week.
Of course, already the idea that we can do such
transformations in context is important, right?
I mean, even if I have proved something about
rotation and color, etc., then it's important
to know that it holds everywhere.
So, it doesn't matter whether I do this in a
“translated” call or somewhere else in the program.
If I do a calculation like this, then
I want this to be true everywhere.
Just as in mathematics, if I write in mathematics,
something like… let me take another law
or other simplification in some sense, let's say
we want to replace division by multiplication.
Yes, that is a mathematics example.
Let's say we have something like x divided
by y. And for whatever reason, I want to
write this with y to the
power of minus one (y^(-1)).
So, the reciprocal of this, and I want to
multiply it by x. Then that is certainly an
appropriate law in mathematics and is
also something that holds in C. If you
think of this as floating-point division
and multiplication etc., then up to rounding
inaccuracies,
this is also something that should be
thought of as a mathematical law in C.
But unfortunately, in a non-mathematical language
like C, that doesn't mean that we can use
this wherever we like in a program.
And why is that not the case?
Well, it's again, this occurrence from last
week that I showed with this minor thing.
So, let's say in Java,
or C, or Python, or
whatever,
you have these two expressions x and y, and they
are actually something like a call to the input
function (which isn't a function in the mathematical
sense, but looks like a function syntactically,
in these languages), then you know that
this is not something that is true, right?
Because it does make a difference whether
you first read the x and then the y or first
read the y and then the x. Providing
two values at the prompt, 2 and 7,
will lead to completely different results
here on the left- and on the right-hand side,
simply because these so-called expressions of
functions are not, in a mathematical sense,
expressions or functions.
So, laws like this, even though they make
sense in arithmetic, cannot be applied in an
effectful setting with side effects.
Okay, and again, of course,
this is a small example.
But think about the same kind of
situation for larger programs with
not just multiplication, division, but really
domain-specific operations like coloring,
etc., for the picture domain. And then
immediately you get power by transforming
expressions, but you can't do that in a
language that doesn't follow expression
style.